Guide to the Alexander Duff Robertson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Alexander Duff Robertson papers
1893-1991
1948-1984
MS 1641
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
9.17
(14 boxes)
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, photographs, writings, diplomas, awards, speeches, certificates, and curricula vitae that document Alexander Duff Robertson's career as a teacher of public health and preventive medicine, an administrator of health organizations, and a spokesman for social medicine. The papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Robertson, Alexander Duff, 1926-1991
General note
Forms part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Richard Moore, 1993.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Arrangement
Arranged in three series: I. Correspondence, 1948-1981. II. Topical Files, 1945-1984. III. Personal Papers, Photographs, and Writings, 1949-1991.
Biographical / Historical
Alexander Duff Robertson was born on April 28,1926, in Dunkfield, England. He received an M.B. from the University of Edinburgh in 1949, a D.P.H. from the University of London in 1955, and an M.D. from the University of Saskatchewan in 1961.
At the University of Edinburgh, Robertson was a researcher in social medicine (1941-1951), a lecturer in public health and social medicine, and a lecturer in the general practice teaching unit (1951-1954). From 1955 to 1958, he was a lecturer in social and preventive medicine at the Royal Free Hospital School of Medicine in London and in public health at the London School of Hygiene and Topical Medicine.
In 1958, Robertson became head of the Department of Social and Preventive Medicine at the University of Saskatchewan where he remained until accepting the executive directorship of the Milbank Memorial Fund in New York City in 1962. During his time at the Milbank Memorial Fund, he launched and developed the Milbank Faculty Fellowship which impacted the development of social medicine. From 1969 until 1990, he worked in several capabilities for the World Health Organization (WHO) beginning with the position of chief of human resources in the Caribbean for two years. From 1972 to 1973, he served as regional advisor for medical education and public health; public health administrator; director of health manpower development; and, finally, as the director of health services in the regional office for the Eastern Mediterranean in Alexandria, Egypt. In 1983, he moved to Geneva, where he was the program manager for staff development and training for WHO until 1986. From 1986 to 1990, he served as special advisor to the director general of WHO for the occupied Arab Territories, including Palestine.
Robertson also held part-time academic positions as a lecturer in Public Health andAdministrative Medicine from 1963 until 1971 at Columbia University and as a lecturer in Public Health (International Health) at Yale University from 1966 to 1971. His publications focused on medical education, community medicine, and social science as related to medicine. He served on numerous boards and at times as an officer in the public sector. He was a leading figure in the field of modern public health especially in the development of health services in the United States. He died on June 29, 1991.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, topical files, photographs, writings, diplomas, awards, speeches, certificates, and curricula vitae that document Alexander Duff Robertson's career as a teacher of public health and preventive medicine, an administrator of health organizations, and a spokesman for social medicine. The papers form part of the Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection.
Medical care; Medicine; Public health; Contemporary Medical Care and Health Policy Collection; Robertson, Alexander Duff, 1926-1991; Milbank Memorial Fund; University of Saskatchewan. Dept. of Social and Preventive Medicine; World Health Organization
- Correspondence, 1948-1981; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged alphabetically within the following sections: Early years; the University of Saskatchewan; the Milbank Memorial Fund; and the World Health Organization (WHO).
  The correspondence primarily documents Alexander Robertson's professional contact with physicians, public health educators and administrators, and professional organizations. The correspondence focuses on the day-to-day operation of each organization such as travel plans, scheduling of meetings, and summary of meetings with staff. A significant amount of the correspondence are copies of his letters. The series includes a substantial amount of correspondence with Maurice Backett, John Brotherston, Mac Dowling, Sheila Hart, J. M. MacIntosh, G. McKerracher, Samuel Milbank, Frederick Mott, and Sam Wolfe.
  The correspondence of the University of Saskatchewan years is dominated by his administrative responsibilities connected with the running of the Department of Social and Preventive Medicine. Also, the correspondence documents issues associated with the Canadian Public Health Association, of which he was chairman from 1960-1961. While at the Milbank Memorial Fund, his correspondence reflects the activities he dealt with on a day-to-day basis in his role as its executive director. There are three folders of correspondence with Samuel Milbank who was Chairman of the Board of Directors and President of the Milbank Memorial Fund. The correspondence highlights issues associated with the Health Research Council of New York City of which Robertson was a member from 1962 to 1969 and Mayor John Lindsay's Advisory Committee on Health Services in New York where he was chairman from 1966 to 1968. The majority of the correspondence focuses on WHO where he worked from 1972 to 1990. The correspondence reflects his administrative duties in the five positions he was assigned to in this organization.
  - Early years, 1948-1954 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - University of Saskatchewan
    - B (General), 1961-1963 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Backett, Maurice, 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Brotherston, John, 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - C-D (General), 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5 - 6)
    - Douglas, T. C., 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - G (General), 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - H-J (General), 1959-1963 (Box 1, Folder 9 - 10)
    - Hart, Sheila, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 11 - 12)
    - Jurcic, Predrag, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - K-L (General), 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Kirkaldy, J. K. S., 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - M (General), 1960-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - MacIntosh, J. M., 1957-1961 (Box 1, Folder 17 - 18)
    - McKerracher, G., 1958-1963 (Box 1, Folder 19 - 20)
    - Mott, Frederick D., 1960-1961 (Box 1, Folder 21 - 22)
    - O-R (General), 1957-1962 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Rockefeller Foundation, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Roemer, Milton, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Roth, F. B., 1958-1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - S (General), 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Scott, Richard, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Silver, George, 1958-1963 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Steele, Robert, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Stewart, C. B., 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - T (General), 1959-1962 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Titmus, R., 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - W (General), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Warren, Michael, 1959-1961 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Willard, H. N., 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Wolfe, Sam, 1958-1961 (Box 2, Folder 37 - 39)
    - Y (General), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Milbank Memorial Fund
    - General, 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 41 - 45)
    - Badgley, Robin, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Lindsay, John, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 47 - 50)
    - Milbank, Sam, 1962-1969 (Box 3, Folder 51 - 53)
    - Congratulatory letters, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Correspondence relating to Robertson's resignation, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 55 - 59)
  - World Health Organization
    - A (General), 1970-1980 (Box 3, Folder 60 - 61)
    - B (General), 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 62 - 64)
    - Backett, Maurice, 1967-1980 (Box 4, Folder 65 - 66)
    - Barnett, Robert, 1973-1978 (Box 4, Folder 67)
    - Barrow, Nita, 1973-1980 (Box 4, Folder 68)
    - Bishop, John, 1973-1980 (Box 4, Folder 69)
    - Blaser, Larry, 1971-1978 (Box 4, Folder 70)
    - Boelen, Charles, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 71)
    - Booth, Roger, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 72)
    - Brago, Ernani, 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 73)
    - Brotherston, John, 1970-1979 (Box 4, Folder 74)
    - Burnery, Leroy, 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 75)
    - C (General), 1967-1979 (Box 4, Folder 76)
    - Chang, Wen, 1973-1980 (Box 4, Folder 77)
    - D (General), 1970-1980 (Box 4, Folder 78 - 79)
    - Dowling, Mac, 1973-1980 (Box 4, Folder 80 - 81)
    - E (General), 1966-1981 (Box 4, Folder 82)
    - Elliott, Katherine, 1971-1980 (Box 4, Folder 83)
    - F (General), 1970-1980 (Box 5, Folder 84 - 85)
    - Ford, David, 1974-1980 (Box 5, Folder 86)
    - Fulop, Tammas, 1974-1979 (Box 5, Folder 87)
    - G-J (General), 1970-1980 (Box 5, Folder 88 - 95)
    - Joorabchi, Bachman, 1973-1981 (Box 5, Folder 96)
    - K (General), 1973-1979 (Box 5, Folder 97 - 98)
    - Katz, Fred, 1976-1980 (Box 5, Folder 99)
    - Khan, Rafique, 1973-1979 (Box 5, Folder 100)
    - L (General), 1965-1980 (Box 5, Folder 101 - 102)
    - Langmuir, Alexander, 1970-1980 (Box 5, Folder 103)
    - M (General), 1970-1980 (Box 5, Folder 104 - 107)
    - Macleod, J. Wendell, 1969-1976 (Box 6, Folder 108)
    - Messih, J. Abdel, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 109)
    - Miller, George, 1974-1980 (Box 6, Folder 110)
    - Mofidi, Chamseddine, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 111)
    - Moore, Richard, 1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 112)
    - N (General), 1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 113)
    - Newell, Kenneth, 1967-1975 (Box 6, Folder 114)
    - O (General), 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 115)
    - P (General), 1970-1980 (Box 6, Folder 116 - 117)
    - Patino, Jose, 1971-1979 (Box 6, Folder 118)
    - Plaja, Antonio, 1970-1975 (Box 6, Folder 119)
    - Prywes, Moshe, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 120)
    - R-S (General), 1967-1980 (Box 6, Folder 121 - 126)
    - Sajid, Abul, 1968-1980 (Box 6, Folder 127)
    - Somers,Kris, 1973-1974 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - Standard, Ken, 1971-1980 (Box 6, Folder 129)
    - Stensland, Per G., 1971-1979 (Box 6, Folder 130)
    - T (General), 1970-1979 (Box 6, Folder 131 - 132)
    - Taba, A. H., 1971-1980 (Box 7, Folder 133)
    - Thuriaux, Michael, 1974-1980 (Box 7, Folder 134)
    - Tiddens, Harmen, 1978-1979 (Box 7, Folder 135)
    - V (General), 1971-1980 (Box 7, Folder 136)
    - W (General), 1971-1980 (Box 7, Folder 137)
    - Whitby, L. G., 1971-1975 (Box 7, Folder 138)
    - Y (General), 1971-1979 (Box 7, Folder 139)
    - Z (General), 1971-1980 (Box 7, Folder 140)
    - Unidentified, 1970-1980 (Box 7, Folder 141 - 143)
- Topical, 1945-1984; Series II
  The series contains professional files that are arranged alphabetically by topical heading. The materials include memoranda, minutes, agendas, financial statements, and reports.
  T he majority of the folders contain information about the various public service organizations of which Robertson was a member during his career, especially when he worked in Saskatchewan and New York. During his time in Saskatchewan, he was involved with the Canadian Public Health Association, the Canadian Medical Association, and the College of General Practice of Canada. Folders filed under College of Physicians and Surgeons in Saskatchewan and the Canadian Labour Congress include speeches, writings, and press releases regarding the Canadian government's proposal on prepaid medical care. Organizations in New York included the Health Services Administration, the Piel Commission, the Health Research Council, and the Task Force on Reorganization of City Government.
  The remaining folders are related to the three institutions that define his professional career. There are six folders from the Milbank Memorial Fund focusing on a leadership resources survey and human resources development in the Caribbean. The World Health Organization(WHO) materials at the headquarters, in the Regional Office for the Eastern Mediterranean and the Pan American Health Organization focus on issues such as a leadership survey and finance. From his time at the Department of Social and Preventive Medicine at the University of Saskatchewan, there are three folders of minutes of meetings as well as reports. Correspondence relating to these organizations can be found in Series I.
  - Association of Canadian Medical Colleges, 1959 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Barbados [brochures], 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 2 - 3)
  - Canadian Medical Association (Saskatchewan Division) Physicians in Public Service, 1959-1960 (Box 8, Folder 4 - 5)
  - Canadian Public Health Association, 1960-1961 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - College of General Practice of Canada, 1957-1963 (Box 8, Folder 7 - 8)
  - Columbia University, 1962-1969 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Federacíon Panamericana de Asociaciones de Facultades de Medicina, 1970-1971 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - International Epidemiological Association, 1956-1971 (Box 8, Folder 11 - 16)
  - Keppel Club Report, 1957-1971 (Box 8, Folder 17 - 20)
  - Milbank Memorial Fund
    - General, 1962-1972 (Box 9, Folder 21)
    - Faculty Fellows, 1970 (Box 9, Folder 22)
    - Human Resources Development in the Caribbean, 1969-1970 (Box 9, Folder 23 - 25)
    - Leadership Resources Survey, 1967-1968 (Box 9, Folder 26 - 28)
    - Staff, 1962-1963 (Box 9, Folder 29)
  - New York City
    - Health Research Council, 1962-1966 (Box 9, Folder 30)
    - Health Services Administration, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 31 - 32)
    - Piel Commission, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 33 - 35)
    - Task Force on Reorganization of City Government, 1966-1967 (Box 9, Folder 36)
  - Rockefeller Grant, 1957-1958 (Box 9, Folder 37)
  - Saskatchewan Association for Adult Education, 1958-1962 (Box 9, Folder 38)
  - Saskatchewan, prepaid medical care
    - Correspondence, 1959-1960 (Box 9, Folder 39 - 40)
    - Canadian Labour Congress, 1956-1960 (Box 10, Folder 41)
    - College of Physicians and Surgeons, 1958-1962 (Box 10, Folder 42 - 44)
    - Press releases and newsletters, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 45)
    - Speeches, 1959-1960 (Box 10, Folder 46)
    - Writings, 1945-1960 (Box 10, Folder 47 - 48)
  - University of London, DPH course, journal, 1955 (Box 10, Folder 49 - 50)
  - University of Saskatchewan, Department of Social and Preventive Medicine, 1961-1963` (Box 10, Folder 51 - 53)
  - World Health Organization
    - Pan American Health Organization
      - Correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 54)
      - General, 1967-1971 (Box 10, Folder 55)
      - Finance, 1969-1971 (Box 10, Folder 56)
      - Confidential files, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 57 - 58)
      - Leadership Survey, 1971 (Box 10, Folder 59)
    - Eastern Mediterranean Regional Office, 1970-1971 (Box 10, Folder 60)
    - Reassignment to headquarters, 1982-1984 (Box 10, Folder 61)
- Personal Papers, Photographs, and Writings, 1949-1991; Series III
  The series is arranged alphabetically into three sections: personal papers, photographs, and writings.
  The personal papers include award certificates, diplomas, resumes, and congratulatory telegrams and letters. Robertson's degree of Doctor of Science, honoris causa, from Union College in 1964 includes a statement describing him as "a pioneering integrator of the behavioral sciences with medicine." The five folders of photographs predominately depict scenes of conferences that Dr. Robertson attended during his career. There is one folder of portraits of Dr. Robertson. His writings include both published works and unpublished manuscripts regarding various issues on medical education, community medicine, and social science as related to medicine. Robertson's speeches comprise the largest portion of the series. They were delivered at a variety of academic, governmental, and international meetings. There are folders with his remarks at the Annual Convention of the Canadian Public Health Association in 1959, the thirty-fifth Anniversary Congress of the Pan American Medical Association in 1960, and the one hundred twenty-fifth celebration of the founding of the Albany Medical Center in 1964 to name a few. Oversize photographs, diplomas, and award certificates are filed at the end of the series.
  - Personal Papers
    - Alistair Robertson diploma, 1893 (Folder 14)
    - Award certificates and diplomas, 1947-1981 (Box 11, Folder 1, Box 13, Folder 2, Folder 14)
    - Curricula vitae, 1975-1991 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Photographs
    - Portraits of Robertson, 1972-1979 (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - Groups, 1948-1984 (Box 11, Folder 4 - 7, Box 13, Folder 1, Folder 14)
  - Writings
    - Speeches
      - Canadian Public Health Association Annual Meeting, 1959 (Box 11, Folder 8)
      - 4th National Scientific Convention of College of General Practice, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 9)
      - 35th Anniversary Congress of Pan American Medical Association, 1960 (Box 11, Folder 10)
      - Introductory Remarks to the Advisory Planning Committee on Medical Care, 1961 (Box 11, Folder 11)
      - American Medical Association Conference on International Health, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 12)
      - Association of Colombian Faculties of Medicine, Cartagena, 1963 (Box 11, Folder 13)
      - Pennsylvania Health Council, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 14)
      - Luncheon for Cornell students, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 15)
      - Inaugural Conference of the Health Manpower Study, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 16)
      - Milbank Memorial Fund/International Epidemiological Association, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 17)
      - Albany Medical Center, 125th Anniversary Celebrations, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 18)
      - White House Conference on Health dinner, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 19)
      - Seminar on epidemiology at Suescun, Colombia, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 20)
      - Milbank Memorial Fund 60th Anniversary, 1965 (Box 11, Folder 21)
      - Remarks and Mayor Lindsay's Talk at the National Health Council, 1966 (Box 11, Folder 22)
      - Lindsay speech to New York Academy of Medicine, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 23)
      - International and Inter-institutional Collaboration in the Health Manpower Study, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 24)
      - Closing speech-Maracay Conference On Health Manpower, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 25)
      - Health Manpower in Bogota, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 26)
      - Milbank Memorial Fund Conference, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 27)
      - Dinner Speech at the Plaza, 1967 (Box 11, Folder 28)
      - Vina del Mar, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 29)
      - Barbados Address to Graduation Ceremony Tercentenary Nursing School, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 30)
      - Care of the Aged (Box 11, Folder 31)
    - Manuscripts, 1957 (Box 12, Folder 32)
    - Publications, 1954-1967 (Box 12, Folder 33 - 35)